Computers
计算机
I've loved them since I've been able to
afford to have my own
自从我懂事以来就比较喜欢计算机
back in the beginning of the modern computer era,
回顾现代计算机时代之初
the 1980s.
二十世纪八十年代
And I've owned a large number of different kinds of computer
我拥有过许多不同类型的计算机
and I've expressed, publicly, loyalty to this kind or that kind.
我公然地表示过对他们各自的忠诚。
But recently my mind has turned, as many people's have,
to this whole business of Free Software.
然而现在我的思想和许多人一样，转向了整个自由软件事业。
There is a lot of confusion about what this means
关于这个所代表的意义，这里有点混乱
and I'd like to help clear it up
我很乐意澄清
because this happens to be a year of celebration,
因为这碰巧发生在喜庆的年份
and I want to help us all celebrate it
我想帮助大家都来庆祝一下
and to look forward to the future of Free Software.
展望自由软件的未来
If you have
如果你
plumbing in your house
房子里有管道
it may be that you don't understand it,
你可能不大理解，
but you may have a friend that does
但是你的朋友或许明白
and they may suggest you move a pipe here, a stopcock there,
他们可能建议你移动管道的位置，装个水龙头，
or a valve somewhere else.
或者阀门之类。
And you're not breaking the law by doing that, are you?
这样做你并没有违犯法律，不是吗？
Because it's your house and you own the plumbing.
因为这是你的房子和你的管道
You can't do that with your computer.
在计算机上你却不能这样做
You can't actually fiddle with your operating system,
如今你却不能随意摆弄自己的操作系统，
and you certainly can't share any ideas you have about
your operating system with other people
并且你不能和其他朋友共享任何关于操作系统的想法
because Apple and Microsoft, who run the two most popular operating systems
因为最流行的两大操作系统厂家苹果和微软
are very firm about that fact that they own that
对此非常固执
and no one else can have anything to do with it.
因此其他人却对此无能为力。
Now this may seem natural to you:
现在你或许自然地想到：
"Why shouldn't they?"
“他们做不了吗？”
But actually, Why can't you do what you like?
然而事实上，你为什么不做自己想做的？
And why can't the community alter, improve, and share?
为什么社区就不能改进和分享她呢？
That's how science works, after all...
毕竟，科学就是这样发展的
All knowledge is free,
所有知识都是自由的，
and all knowledge is shared in good science.
有价值的科学知识都是共享的。
If it isn't -- it's bad science
如果不共享，就算不上好的学问
and it's a kind of tyranny.
这是一种对知识的禁锢。
And this is, really, where it all started
然而这的确是一个全新的开始，
A man called Richard Stallman
一个叫理查德.斯托曼(Richarc Stallman)的人
decided 25 years ago, almost to this very day, to
二十五年前决定
write a whole new operating system from the ground up.
从头写一个全新的操作系统。他几乎每天都为之奋斗。
He called this system GNU which stands for "GNU is Not Unix"
他称这个系统为GNU(GNU is Not Unix)
because it isn't Unix,
因为她不是Unix
it is similar to Unix in many ways,
在很多方面与Unix很类似
but every element of it, every module, every little section of the code
但是她的每个元素、每个模块、每小段代码
(and it's a gigantic code because it's to run on many platforms)
(她是一个巨大的代码集合，因为可以运行在多种平台上)
is run by the community, run by coders "out there"
被社区使用，也被社区以外的编程人员使用着
who are welcomed in to the GNU community, to help improve the software.
他们被欢迎进入GNU社区，帮助改进软件。
Every "distro", as they are called, every distribution of GNU
他们所说的每一个"distro"，即每一个GNU发行版
is tested, worked upon, and refined
被测试，完善，优化
by people whose only interest is creating the perfect operating system
靠的是那些只对创造完美操作系统感兴趣的人
that can be used across the spectrum of platforms and by as many users as possible.
她可以被不同平台上尽可能多的用户使用。
Now, there came a time when the kernel, which
is the central part of an operating system,
needed to be written.
现在当需要写个内核时，便进入了一个新时期，因为内核是操作系统的核心部分。
And a man called Linus Torvalds, of whom you may have heard,
一个叫Linus Torvalds的人，你或许听过他，
wrote the kernel and it was named after his name,
写了一个内核，并用他的名字命名，
Linux (line-ucks)
Linux(line-ucks)
or Linux (Lin-ucks) as some people pronounce it.
或者像其他人读的那样Linux(Lin-ucks)
And Linux is the kernel that runs within GNU
Linux是在GNU里运行的内核
and I'm here
在这里我
simply to remind you that GNU and Linux are the twin pillars
of the Free Software community,
只是提醒你，GNU和Linux是自由软件社区的两大栋梁，
people who believe, and this is the important part,
重要的是，人们认为
that software should be Free,
软件应该是自由的，
that the community of users should be allowed to adapt it,
用户社区应该被允许改编代码
adopt it, change it, to improve it, and to spread those improvements around,
改编她、修改她、改进她，并把这些改进公布给大众，
like science.
就像科学。
That's basically what it is saying.
这是科学最基本的。
In the same way that good scientists share everything
and all knowledge is open and free
同时有一些好的科学家共享所有东西，所有知识都是开放、自由的
so it should be with an operating system.
因此操作系统应该也是这样的。
So, if you're a supporter of GNU,
因此，如果你支持GNU，
if you're a support of Linux, and the Free Software Foundation,
如果你支持Linux和自由软件基金会，
you are probably wondering "Well what can I do?"
你很可能想知道“我能做什么？”
The most obvious thing you can do is use a GNU/Linux operating system
on your own computer.
最简单的就是，在你的电脑上使用GNU/Linux操作系统
It's much easier than you might think.
这可能比你想像的要简单得多
Go to the website "gnu.org" and see if you can find an operating system
that suits you.
进入网站"gnu.org"，看看能否找到适合你的操作系统。
Probably, if you like a good graphical user-interface,
或许，如果你喜欢一个好的图形用户界面，
something like g-New-Sense, gNewSense
就像g-New-Sense，gNewSense
You'll see it there on gnu.org.
你可以在gnu.org看到她。
Or, if you're a really smart cookie,
否则，如果你是个真正聪明的家伙，
you might want to do your own coding.
你可能想自己编写代码。
You might want to contribute to the sum of knowledge
你可能想做贡献
that makes GNU and Linux what they are.
来推动GNU和Linux的发展
Either way,
另外，
I hope you will join me
我希望你们能加入到我们当中
in wishing GNU a very happy twenty-fifth birthday.
祝愿GNU有一个快乐的二十五岁生日。
Lets do that now, actually...
事实上，让我们从现在开始吧……
Happy birthday, GNU!
生日快乐，GNU！
Twenty-five years old.
二十五岁了。
The operating system of the future.
未来的操作系统。
Freedom!
自由！
Chocolaty good.
巧克力不错。
The tastiest operating system in the world...
世界上最美味的操作系统……
and it's all free.
完全是自由的。
Captions: Gregory Maxwell
英文字幕: Gregory Maxwell
中文字幕: 孔建军(jianjun@zeuux.org)
哲思自由软件社区(www.zeuux.org)